Dr. Shravan Vudumu, Ph.D.

Technical Manager - Controls and Systems Engineering | Data Analytics, Machine Learning - Georgia Tech

Summary

Technical Manager with a doctorate degree in Mechanical Engineering and master's degree in Management. Over fourteen years of work experience in a multinational corporation developing control algorithms for complex systems and implementing model based designs. Proven ability to coach, lead and manage teams to perform engineering data analysis, simulation based product development, optimize electromechanical devices with embedded software and resolving technical challenges. Successfully coached engineers globally. Expanding skills with master's degree in Data Analytics specializing in Business Data Analytics and Machine Learning. No work authorization required.

EDUCATION

Georgia Institute of Technology, USA

Master of Science in Data Analytics

• Specialization: Business Data Analytics, Machine Learning

University of Illinois, Urbana - Champaign, USA

Master of Science in Management

• Specialization: Business Data Management and Communication

Missouri University of Science and Technology, USA

Ph.D. Mechanical Engineering

• Dissertation title: "Experimental and Computational Investigations of Hydrogen Safety, Dispersion and Combustion for Transportation Applications"

Indian Institute of Technology - Madras, India

M. Tech Energy Technology and B. Tech Mechanical Engineering

• Thesis title: "Modeling of a Diesel Engine for Speed Control". Minor: Industrial Engineering

Work Experience

Cummins Inc., Columbus, Indiana, USA

Aug 2010 - Present

- Controls, Software and Electronics Engineering Technical Manager
- Dynamic Systems and Controls (DS&C) Technical Manager
- Dynamic Systems and Controls (DS&C) Technical Advisor

Management and Technical Coaching Experience

- Managed a team of engineers, group leads and contractors to successfully deliver Cummins' Controls Performance Features and data analysis deliverables for multiple diesel and spark ignition engine programs for on-highway and off-highway applications with wide range of air handling system architecture complexities.
- Supervised multiple engine development programs by managing deadlines and prioritizing tasks. Effectively addressed roadblocks by identifying root cause and implementing a robust seven-step problem solving process. Fostered a collaborative team environment through stakeholders coordination. Skilled in project leadership.
- Coached and developed local Brazil and China control systems calibration and validation engineering talent that was needed to maintain Cummins' technology leadership in critical international markets. Built communication bridges with global engineering teams (China, India, UK, and Brazil). This included on-site support at East Asia Research and Development Center in China and at Cummins-Dongfeng joint venture research facilities.
- Aided in the development and restructuring of Cummins' technical documents, requirements and engineering practices to ensure global adoption and for engine development integration. Promoted adherence to the process.
- Co-ordinated Simulation Based Product Development and next generation engine architecture evaluation efforts in Cummins' East Asia Research and Development Center in China. Provided expertise to define scope, assess model capabilities, evaluate complex engine system architectures and to resolve technical challenges.
- Led the development of Cummins' AUTOSAR air handling controller by understanding stakeholder voices, developing technical requirements, facilitating cross functional collaboration, analyzing performance data and by participating in the delivery of embedded software. Managed engineers for design calibration and validation.
- Proactively addressed resource gaps by collaborating with global technical teams, HR, universities and consultancy firms to secure top talent (technical contributors, group leads, interns and contractors) and avoided delays on key Cummins' controls and systems engineering deliverables. Empowered engineers to launch successful careers.

GPA: 3.6/4.0Aug 2023 - Present

GPA: 4.0/4.0 Aug 2022 - July 2023

GPA: 4.0/4.0

Aug 2006 - July 2010

GPA: 8.0/10.0 Aug 2001 - May 2006

Technical Contributions and Experience

- Engineered improvements and calibrated model-based air handling controller for multiple Cummins engines to achieve higher fuel economy, optimal transient performance, and reduced emissions in various driving conditions.
- Proven track record in development, calibration and data analysis of model-based controllers for complex systems, virtual sensors, electromechanical devices and diagnostics algorithms for different engine architectures.
- In-depth experience in collecting data from test cells and prototype vehicles with data acquisition systems. Data analytics for performance and on-board diagnostic evaluations, and reporting outcomes to stakeholders.
- Developed MATLAB data analytics tools to visualize key findings from vehicles, test cells and emission cycles.
- Expertise in engine simulations to develop new control system design concepts for various advanced air handling system architectures using GT-POWER engine simulation software and Simulink tools.
- Skilled in applying engineering data analysis principles to evaluate the performance of intake air systems, EGR systems, heat exchangers, turbomachinery, smart sensors, device drivers, combustion, and engine emissions.
- Experience in developing embedded software designs and creating ECM builds. Successfully tested prototype software at unit and system level for validating functionality on open-loop and closed-loop test benches.
- Designed a new model-based on-board diagnostic (OBD) algorithm for the air handling subsystem to detect failures on low-cost engine platforms (a six-sigma project). Performed simulations, data analytics and system validation.
- Developed a model-based turbocharger protection design to prevent engines from failure (a six-sigma project).

RESEARCH AND TEACHING EXPERIENCE

- Characterized the fluid dynamics of new/alternative transportation fuels to ensure their safe and proper use. Research was funded by US Department of Transportation (through Research and Innovative Technology Administration's National University Transportation Center) and the **Department of Defense' Defense** Logistics Agency (through Air Force Research Laboratory).
- Played a key role in setting-up Missouri's first hydrogen fueling station together with operating a hydrogen powered commuter bus to develop, demonstrate, and evaluate safe use of hydrogen-based technologies.
- Performed research on internal combustion engines powered by alternative and conventional fuels to characterize their unique performance, combustion, and emissions characteristics.
- Developed mathematical diesel engine models for optimization of engine controllers and a critical data acquisition system to acquire real time engine data with in-cylinder instrumentation for model validations.
- Developed, taught and graded engineering courses. GM PACE (General Motors Partners for Advancement of Collaborative Engineering Education) sponsored project for integrating simulations in engineering curriculum.

Publications

- As doctoral researcher, published six international journal and conference papers (IJHE, ASME, Energy).
- Published research documents for US DOT's repository and Cummins' internal technical documents for engineers.

Data Analytics and Engineering Software Skills

- Data Analytics Skills: wrangling, modeling, machine learning, statistical analysis, optimization, visualization
- Data Analytics Software: R, Python, Power BI, Tableau, SQL, Git version control, Excel, Arena, Minitab
- Engineering Software: MATLAB, Simulink, GT-POWER, data acquisition tools (Calterm, IndiCom, LabView)

Data Analytics Master's Degree Projects

- Data analytics of Divvy bikes, a ride sharing system in Chicago.
- Machine learning algorithms for evaluating credit applications.
- Shortest path evaluations in road networks. Ingredient swap recommendations.
- Predicting house prices with machine learning. Time series analysis of inflation. • Calorie conscious diet planning on budget. Optimizing airport check-in simulations.
- Data-driven exploration of superstore sales and inventory to uncover insights.
- Financial modeling, capital budgeting of firms and portfolio optimization.

 $R,\ Python\ -pandas,\ geopandas$

R - XGBoost, neural network

SQL, Python, RegEx

Python - pandas, numpy

Python - pulp, simpy

Power BI. Tableau

Excel - Optimization

CERTIFICATIONS, HONORS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- Selected in "Outstanding Under 35 Young Scientists Committee" at "HySyDays 2007, Second World Congress of Young Scientists on Hydrogen Energy" organized by the Inter-University Research Center for Sustainable Development, Sapienza University of Rome, Italy.
- Recipient of the prestigious US Department of Transportation's (Research and Innovative Technology Administration) National University Transportation Center (NUTC) assistantship.
- Merit scholarship and tuition waiver (2001-06). Member of ASME, SAE, AIAA, IJHE (2009-10).
- Earned Six Sigma Green Belt certification (2015). Received cash award for filing a patent application (2015).
- Completed **Systems Engineering Certification** sponsored by Cummins and University of Detroit-Mercy.
- Recipient of Cummins' Business Impact Award for Leadership and Contributions from Vice President.